Guide to the Anne Ramsay Somers Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Anne Ramsay Somers papers
1955-2006
MS 1237
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
26.26
The papers consist of correspondence, project files, speeches and presentations, writings and topical files all relating to health insurance and health care, particularly in its financial aspects in the United States, geriatric medicine, and long-term care financing. Important correspondents include Odin W. Anderson, Robert M. Ball, Frederick W. Brown, Wilbur J. Cohen, Merlin K. DuVal, Melvin A. Glasser, Philip R. Lee, James Mackenzie, Robert J. Myers, Ernest W. Saward, and Robert M. Sigmond. The writings include texts articles, letters to the editor, and reviews of published monographs. Also included are speeches, presentations, and essays written between 1968 and 2003. The project and topical files contain memoranda, reports, clippings, research notes, and correspondence from government agencies, individuals, and private groups. There are also several reports on the New Jersey Department of Health in 1974 and a script for a series of television programs featuring health and hospital programs in New Jersey (1970). In addition there are chronological files of professional meetings attended by Somers with related correspondence, printed matter, and writings. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Somers, Anne Ramsay
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Anne Ramsay Somers, 1980, 1983, and 1989. Gift of Margaret Somers, 2007.
General
Forms part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection, Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and additions: I. General Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Project Files.
Scope and Contents
The Anne Ramsay Somers Papers consist of 10 linear feet of office files which contain correspondence, project files, and writings. They extend from 1955 to 1978, although the bulk of the papers covers the years 1960 to 1978.
The Somers Papers are incomplete; they contain no material documenting her academic appointments. In addition, they provide only limited information on her service in professional organizations, on her work as a consultant, and on her membership on the Health Insurance Benefits Advisory Council. The papers do, however, contain correspondence with a number of significant figures in health care and health policy, and they provide extensive coverage of her publications and speeches. The papers are organized in three series: GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, WRITINGS, and PROJECT FILES.
Series I GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE is arranged alphabetically and dates primarily from the mid 1960s through 1978. The series contains exchanges with acquaintances, colleagues, professional organizations, public officials and others, and it covers a wide range of areas in health and health policy. Somers corresponded with important figures in public health and health economics such as: Odin W. Anderson, Robert M. Ball, Frederick W. Brown, Wilbur J. Cohen, Melvin A. Glasser, Philip R. Lee, James Mackenzie, Robert J. Myers, Ernest W. Saward, Robert M. Sigmond. Her exchanges with Brown, Du Val, Glasser, Lee and Myers contain lengthy, informal discussions of her views on health care and health insurance. However, most of the series is limited to one or a few exchanges with specific correspondents or is routine in nature.
Series II, WRITINGS, is divided into two sections,Monographs and Speeches and Shorter Writings.Monographs is arranged chronologically by title and covers books and book chapters which Somers authored or co-authored between 1960 and 1977. The section includes drafts, outlines, correspondence, reviews and other items.
The Speeches and Shorter Writings section spans the years 1968 to 1977, although most of the material dates from 1969 to 1974. The section is arranged chronologically by the date papers were first presented or published. Revisions of papers which were subsequently published or presented (including those with variant titles) are filed with the original version of the paper. The section includes speech texts, reprints, tear sheets, and correspondence. The major topics represented are hospital administration, the role of hospitals in health care, consumer health education, and health insurance.
Series III, PROJECT FILES, dates from 1966 to 1979 and covers a variety of Somers' professional activities, including organizations, conferences, and panels on which she served; consulting work; informal consultations with colleagues; and production of a television series on health services organization, financing and health consumerism. The series also includes a few materials from her appointment to the Health Insurance Benefits Advisory Council.
The series includes more than twenty separate organizations and projects, although the coverage for each is very limited. Most of the activities described in the series relate to consumer health education.
The papers are part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection, which also includes the papers of Somers' husband, Herman M. Somers (Ms. Group No. 1238).
Biographical / Historical
Anne Ramsay Somers, educator, author, and consultant, has been an influential figure in American public health policy, hospital administration, prepaid health insurance plans, and consumer health education. Born in Memphis, Tennessee, in 1913, she was educated at Vassar College (B.A., 1935) and the University of North Carolina (1939-1940). Her early interests were labor economics and industrial relations, and she served as educational director of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union from 1937 to 1942 and as a labor economist with the U.S. Department of Labor from 1943 to 1946.
In 1947, she married Herman Miles Somers, then an economist at the U.S. Office of War Mobilization and Reconversion, and spent the next seven years studying and raising a family. In 1954 she and her husband published Workmen's Compensation, their first collaborative work. The study was the first to fully emphasize the importance of the health benefits provided under Workmen's Compensation. After 1954 the Somers became gradually more involved in the area of health economics and in 1957 Anne was appointed a research associate (1957-1963) at Haverford College, where her husband was professor and chairman of the Department of Political Science (1948-1963).
They published a second joint work on health care, Doctors, Patients, and Health Insurance, in 1961. As the first modern full-scale exposition of the organization and financing of health care in the United States, the monograph was widely acclaimed and brought them a great deal of recognition.
During the 1960s and 1970s Anne Somers published a succession of incisive and influential studies of American health care and health policy: Medicare and the Hospitals, 1967, with Herman Somers; Health Care in Transition, 1971; and Health and Health Care: Policies in Perspective, 1977, with Herman Somers. Anne Somers has also published in the field of hospital administration and has conducted studies exploring new areas of health policy such as geriatrics, health education, violence, and various aspects of preventive medicine.
Besides her extensive work as a consultant in the public and private sectors, Somers has served as a research associate in the Industrial Relations Section, Princeton University, since 1964 and as professor of community and family medicine, College of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey-Rutgers Medical School since 1971. From 1972 to 1974 she was also director of the Office of Consumer Health Education, College of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, and she has participated in policy making and administration in a variety of other positions, including one term as a member of the Health Insurance Benefits Advisory Council (1972-1975).
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Health education; Health planning; Health services administration; Health insurance; Medical care; Medicine, Preventive; Public health -- New Jersey; Public health -- United States; Educators; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Anderson, Odin W. (Odin Waldemar), 1914-2003; Ball, R. M. (Robert M.); Brown, Frederick Winfield, 1908-; Cohen, Wilbur J. (Wilbur Joseph), 1913-1987; DuVal, Merlin K., 1922-2006; Glasser, Melvin A.; Lee, Philip R. (Philip Randolph), 1924-; Mackenzie, James; Myers, Robert James, 1904-; Saward, Ernest W.; Sigmond, Robert M., 1920-; Somers, Anne Ramsay; New Jersey. State Department of Health; United States. Department of Health and Human Services; American Diabetes Association
- Correspondence, 1955-1978; Series I; 3 linear feet (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by personal or corporate name.
  - A - Am (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - An - Ay (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Hospital Association, 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Medical Association, 1955-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General note
    See also: box 4, Folder 75 See also: box 4, Folder 85
  - Anderson, Odin W., 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges, 83rd Annual Meeting, 1972 November 2-4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges, 84th Annual Meeting, 1973 November 4-7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B - Bl (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bo - Bu (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bachman, Leonard, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Badgley, Robin F., 1966, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ball, Robert M., 1976, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bauer, Katharine G., 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Beall, J. Glenn, Jr., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bergen, Stanley, Jr., 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berke, Mark, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bernstein, Arthur, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Blue Cross Association
    See: box 4, Folder 58
  - Blue Cross-Blue Shield National Health Achievement Awards, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bowers, John Z., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Breslow, Lester, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brewster, Agnes, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brian, Earl W., 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    See also: box 19, Folder 20
  - Brookings Institution
    See: box 4, Folder 74
  - Brown, Frederick W., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - C - Ch (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cl - Cy (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cathcart, H. Robert, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cleveland, Harlan, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cohen, Wilbur J., 1969, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cohen, William S., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Coleman, J. Douglas, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cooper, John, 1971, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - D (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Darley, Ward, 1965-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Davies, Nicholas E., 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Duffy, Benedict J., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - DuVal, Merlin K., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - E (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Ebaugh, Franklin G., Jr., 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - F - Fi (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Fl - Fu (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fielding, Jonathan E., 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Flanders, Caroline, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Follman, Joseph F., 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Friedlander, Edward M., 1967-1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    See also: box 2, Folder 33
  - Fullerton, William D., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - G (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - General Research Corporation, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ginsburg, Woodrow L., 1966, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Glaser, Robert J., 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Glasser, Melvin A., 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Gordber, Sir George, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Gooden, Opal, 1968, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Grobosch, Joseph, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - H - He (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Hi - Hu (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Hart, Philip A., 1971 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Health Facilities Planning Council for New Jersey, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Health Insurance Association of America
    See: box 2, Folder 28
  - Health Policy Plank, the Platform Committee of the Democratic National Convention, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Hill, Lawrence A., 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Hollander, Edward D., 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Hospital and Health Planning Council of Metropolitan New Jersey, Inc., 1967, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    General
    See: box 1, Folder 3
  - Hospitals
  - Hughes, Richard J., 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - I (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Ingelfinger, Franz J., 1968-1977 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Inquiry, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - International Health Advisory Council and Booz, Allen and Hamilton, Inc., Tucson, Arizona, 1976 April 29-May 1 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    See also: box 18, Folder 4
  - J (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Johnson (Robert Wood) Foundation, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Jones, Wanda J., 1970-1977 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - K (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Kaiser Foundation Health Plan, Inc., 1966-1977 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Kandle, Roscoe P., 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Kauffman, John W., 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Kellogg (W.K.) Foundation
  - Kissick, William L., 1965-1978 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - L - Lev (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Lew - Ly (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Lanier, Jack O., 1973, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Lee, Philip R., 1969-1976 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Levi, Joseph, 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Little (Arthur D.), Inc., 1970, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - M - May (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Me - My (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Mackenzie, James, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - McNerney, Walter J., 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - McNulty, Matthew F., Jr., 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Medical Care
    See: box 5, Folder 78
  - Medical Economics, 1968-1978 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Milbank Memorial Fund, 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - The Modern Hospital, 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Moss, Frank E., 1971 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Mott, Frederick D., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Myers, Robert J., 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - N (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - National Academy of Sciences, Institute of Medicine Conference, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - National Advisory Commission on Health Manpower, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - National Clearinghouse, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - New England Journal of Medicine
    See: box 2, Folder 31
  - New Jersey Department of Health, 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    See also: box 3, Folder 49
  - New Jersey Department of Human Services, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - New Jersey Department of Institutions and Agencies, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - New Jersey Health Facilities Planning Council
    See: box 3, Folder 36
  - New Jersey Hospital and Health Planning Council
    See: box 3, Folder 39
  - New Jersey Hospital Association, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - New Jersey Regional Medical Program, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - New Jersey Rehabilitation Commission, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - O (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Owen, Jack W.
    See: box 4, Folder 70
  - P (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Patullo, Andrew, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Pechman, Joseph A., 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Pellegrino, Edmund D., 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Pollicoff, Leonard D., 1972-1979 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Prism, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Q - Ri (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Ro - Ry (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Reidel, Donald C., 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Rice, Dorothy P.
    See: box 5, Folder 89
  - Richardson, Elliot L., 1966-1971 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Roemer, Milton J., 1971-1978 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Rogers, Paul G., 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Sa - Sh (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Si - So (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Sp - Sw (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Saward, Ernest W., 1971, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Sheps, Cecil G., 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Sigmond, Robert M., 1966-1977 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Silver, George A., 1961-1974 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Stokes, Joseph, Jr., 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - T (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Thompson, Frank, Jr., 1967-1975 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Tierney, Thomas M.
  - Tufo, Henry M., 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - U - V (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - United Hospital Fund of New York, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    See also: box 2, Folder 28
  - United Mine Workers of America, Welfare and Retirement Fund
    See: box 2, Folder 33
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    See also: box 2, Folder 18
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1971-1978 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Volker, J.F., 1974 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - W - Wh (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Wi - Wy (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Weed, Lawrence L., 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Weissman, Arthur
    See: box 3, Folder 48
  - Wescott, Lloyd B., 1965-1977 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Williams, Harrison A., 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Willis, David P.
    See: box 4, Folder 61
  - Wolkstein, Irwin
  - X - Y - Z (Box 6, Folder 97)
- Writings, 1961-1977; Series II; 6 linear feet (12 boxes)
  Series II is organized in two sections, Monographs and Speeches and Shorter Writings. Each section is arranged chronologically.
  - Monographs
    - Doctors, Patients and Health Insurance, with Herman M. Somers
      - Reviews, correspondence and related material, 1960 September-1961 May, 1961 July-1964 (Box 6a, Folder 1-3)
    - A Guide to the Management of Negotiated Hospital, Surgical and Medical Care Benefits, the Foundation on Employee Health, Medical Care and Welfare, Inc.: published text, 1961 November (Box 6a, Folder 4)
    - The Pediatrician, the Hospital and the Community, with Andrew Hunt, Jr. and Robert Sigmond
      - Correspondence and progress reports, 1962-1964 June (Box 6a, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence and outline, 1964 July-1965 (Box 6a, Folder 6)
    - Promoting the Group Practice of Medicine, report of the National Conference on Group Practice, U.S.D.H.E.W. report, 1967 October 19-21 (Box 6a, Folder 7)
    - The Paradox of Health Care: Crisis Born of Progress, National Academy of Sciences: correspondence, reviews and text, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Hospital Regulation: the Dilemma of Public Policy: reviews, correspondence and related material, 1969-1971 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - The Kaiser Permanente Medical Care Program: One Valid Solution to the Problem of Health Care Delivery in the United States, edited by Anne R. Somers: correspondence, reviews and press releases, 1970-1972 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Health Care in Transition
      - Correspondence, reviews and related material, 1971 March-July (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, reviews and comments, 1971 August-1974 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Remarks re: the receipt of the American College of Hospital Administrators 1973 Book of the Year Award: text and correspondence, 1973 February 23 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - State Regulation of Hospitals and Health Care: The New Jersey Story, Blue Cross Reports, Research Series II: correspondence and text, 1973 July (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Health and Health Care: Perspectives 1954-1976, with Herman M. Somers: contract, correspondence and reviews, 1973-1977 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Speeches and Shorter Writings
    - "Some Suggested Principles for Community Health Planning and for the Role of the Teaching Hospital," The Journal of Medical Education: reprint, 1968 April (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Secretary's Regional Conference on Health Care Costs: program, 1969 January 8-10 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - "Doctors, Patients and Insurance," Illinois Health Improvement Association, Springfield: correspondence, speech text and programs, 1969 January 14-16 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Hospital Planning for Greater Boston, Inc.: annual report and notes, 1969 January 28 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - National Research Council, Drug Research Board, Conference on Continuing Education for Physicians in the Use of Drugs, Washington, D.C.: correspondence, agenda and speech notes, 1969 February 5 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - "How Does Comprehensive Health Care Relate to the Health Care Industry?" American Congress of Rehabilitation Medicine, Houston (Texas): correspondence, speech text and conference material, 1969 February 20-21 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - "Planning for New Jersey and the Future," New Jersey League of Nursing: correspondence and speech, 1969 March 3 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - "The Central Role of the Hospital in Community Health Services," Georgia Hospital Association and Georgia State College, Atlanta: speech texts, 1969 March 27-29 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - "The Central Role of the Hospital in Community Health Services," St. Cloud Hospital, St. Cloud (Minnesota): correspondence and report, 1969 April 17 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - "Meeting Public Expectations in the Delivery of Health Care," Academy of Hospital Public Relations, St. Louis: correspondence and speech text, 1969 April 18 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Washington University Seminar on hospital financing: notes, 1969 April 19 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - St. Mary's Hospital, Milwaukee: correspondence and reports, 1969 April 26 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - "Social Concepts in the Financing of Hospitals," Hospital Financial Management Association, New York City: correspondence, speech text and program, 1969 May 8 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - "Meeting Manpower Requirements Through Increased Productivity," Hospital Credit and Accounting Institute: correspondence and program, 1969 May 9 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - "Technology, Economics and the Doctor-Patient Relationship," University of Rochester School of Medicine: speech text and correspondence, 1969 May 9 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - "The Central Role of the Hospital in Community Health Services," Michigan Hospital Association: speech excerpt, program and correspondence, 1969 May 15-16 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - "Comprehensive Health Care: Some Suggestions for Implementation," Dunciger Institute for Health Sciences, Menorah Medical Center, Kansas City (Missouri): speech text and programs, 1969 May 15- (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Greater Cincinnati Hospital Council, Conference on Patient Care and Public Policy: correspondence, notes and conference material, 1969 May 21-22 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - "Technology, Economics and the Doctor-Patient Relationship," University of Kentucky College of Medicine: correspondence and speech introduction, 1969 May 23 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - "A National Health System: Comments on Dr. Roemer's Paper," The Catholic Hospital Association, Minneapolis: correspondence and speech, 1969 June 10-13 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - "The Central Role of the Hospital in Community Health Services," Connecticut Hospital Association, Hartford (Connecticut): correspondence and speech text, 1969 June 18 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - "Improving and Expanding Community Health Care," International Ladies Garment Workers Union, New Brunswick (New Jersey): conference material and notes, 1969 June 20-22 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Intermountain Regional Medical Program, Salt Lake City: correspondence and agenda, 1969 June 26 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - "Long-Range Trends and Short-Range Politics," Medical Student Institute, Washington, D.C.: speech text, 1969 July 9 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - "The Options Before Us," Institute for the Study of Health and Society, Washington, D.C.: speech excerpt, 1969 July 9 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Round table re: "The Family Physician's Role in Health Insurance," Patient Care Management Concepts, New York City: correspondence and agenda, 1969 July 18 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - "Focus on Planning" and "Hospital Reimbursement and Areawide Planning," Hospital Financial Management Educational Foundation, Columbus (Ohio): speech texts and correspondence, 1969 July 28 (Box 8, Folder 42)